Carlos A. Fernandes dos Santos

157 City Island Way – E14 0TL – London, United Kingdom \bigstar 24 November 1985 • \square +44 (0) 7789 270394

☐ carlosalexandre.santos@outlook.com • in www.linkedin.com/in/carlosafsantos/
☐ github.com/carlosasantos

Summary

Data professional with a PhD in Physics and 8+ years of experience in using Data Science and Artificial Intelligence to solve challenging academic and business problems.

Experienced in designing, building and productionising machine learning based solutions, and at managing teams to deliver said solutions, at scale.

Solid skills in python programming, mathematics, algorithms, MLOps and cloud platforms.

Experience

Microsoft London, UK

Senior Specialised AI Cloud Solution Architect

Jul 2021 - Present

Description: Cloud Solution Architect, specialised in AI and Data Science on Azure, within the Microsoft Customer Experience and Success organisation. This role focuses on the strategy, design, and implementation of AI services and solutions for global customers. Main responsibilities include:

- Designing and building scalable AI/ML solutions that drive business value for customers. This is achieved by working with customers to develop Proofs of Concept and/or Minimum Viable Products, while ensuring a responsible use of AI.
- Supporting customers in the adoption of Machine Learning Operations (MLOps)
- Identifying and collaborating in the development of code and documentation assets that can be reused to further scale the adoption of Azure AI services.
- Liaising with Microsoft Engineering teams to remove key blockers and drive product improvements, based on Customer feedback.

Accenture, Applied Intelligence

London, UK

Data Science Manager Data Science Consultant Dec 2019 - Jun 2021 Oct 2018 - Nov 2019

Description: Data Science Manager within the Applied Intelligence team, and part of the wider Strategy & Consulting practice. Key achievements include:

- Leading a global cross-functional team of Data Scientists, ML Engineers, Data Engineers and Frontend developers to develop
 digital solutions to improve and optimise processing plants for a mining organisation. These solutions, developed in Python and
 deployed in Azure, are to be scaled to multiple mining plants globally, and support the business goal of generating \$100M of value
 from data analytics in 2020.
- Managing, as the Data Science Lead, a team of 7 data scientists on a large project aiming to develop a solution that identifies product trends based on social media, for a large retail client. The solution is developed in Python, leverages NLP and ML techniques, and is deployed in GCP.
- Managing a team of 5 analysts and consultants. Key responsibilities include finding and securing chargeable projects, coaching and support with career development.

Deloitte UK London, UK

Senior Consultant / Data Scientist Consultant / Data Scientist Sep 2017 - Oct 2018

Feb 2016 - Aug 2017

Description: Data Scientist within the Risk Analytics team and part of the wider Risk Advisory Practice. The role consists in developing data science solutions to help organisations, within financial services, to gain market insights, minimise risk or drive process improvement and efficiency. Key achievements include:

- O Developing a policy violation predictive model for a professional service firm, using Random Forests.
- Developing optimisation models for a Payment Protection Insurance (PPI) complaint operation, with a workforce of around 1000 people and approximately 100 000 complaints, for a large retail bank.
- Managing and developing a cognitive proof of concept, for a big four UK bank, to scrape and analyse large sets of news articles, in an automated way, aiming to support the credit underwriting process. This PoC was developed in Python and leveraged NLP and ML techniques.
- Developing of emotion, sentiment and topic models, leveraging NLP techniques in Python, to analyse audio files transcriptions, to automate the auditing process of several thousand hours of recorded phone calls, for a large insurance company.

Istituto Nazionale di Fisica Nucleare - Sezione di Trieste

Trieste, Italy

Postdoctoral Research Fellow

Mar 2014 - Jan 2016

Description: Postdoctoral research fellowship in the field of experimental particle physics, focused on the research and development of gaseous photon detectors dedicated to the studies of the nucleon structure. The work performed envisaged the upgrade of a large area detector of a major experiment at a world leading physics laboratory in Geneva – CERN, where a significant part of R&D activities took place. The main activities included:

- \circ Processing and analysis of comprehensive data sets to validate the R&D carried out. Data processing and analysis performed using C/C++, Matlab and others, in Windows and Unix environments.
- Monte Carlo Simulations to study physics interactions.
- Development of hardware.
- o Management of data acquisition leading to a deep understanding of complex structured data.
- Supervision of undergraduate students in R&D activities.

Education

Ph.D. in Physics Oct 2009 – Feb 2014

University of Aveiro Aveiro, Portugal

Description: Research thesis under the title "Thick-Microstructures for MPGDs: Simulation and Experimental Studies". The research work was carried out between Aveiro, CERN and INFN Trieste.

M.Sc. in Engineering Physics

Oct 2008 - Jul 2009

University of Aveiro Aveiro, Portugal

Description: Research dissertation under the title: "Simulation of Electron Avalanches in Radiation Gaseous Detectors".

B.Sc. in Engineering Physics

Sep 2004 - Oct 2008

University of Aveiro Aveiro, Portugal

Description: Research project under the title: "Energy Weighting in a Single Photon Counting X-ray Detector based in a MHSP".

Personal Skills and Competencies

Languages

- English ■■■■ | Native Language Italian ■■■■ | Level B2

Soft Skills

- Problem Solver
 Good Communicator
- Critical ThinkerCurious
- Storyteller

Technical Skills

- PythonMatlab<l
- MatlabR
- Scikit-learnTensorFlow / KerasAmazon Web ServicesQuantum Computing
- Machine Learning / Deep LearningMLOpsExcelMT_EX

Certifications

- Azure Al Engineer Associate
- Azure Data Scientist Associate
- Azure AI Fundamentals
- Azure Fundamentals
- o Google Cloud Platform Professional Data Engineer
- Google Cloud Platform Professional Cloud Architect
- Google Cloud Platform Associate Cloud Engineer
- o MIT Quantum Computing Fundamentals Online Program a two-course certificate program to establish a foundation of knowledge for understanding the business implications of quantum computing.